בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is נ"ד, Nun Dalet, good
ערב פסח, erev Pesach, and we pick up on נ"ג עמוד ב׳
Nun Gimmel amud bet about ten lines from the bottom, we pick
up on about maybe fifteen lines from the bottom, תנו רבנן אם
גאל יגאל, Tanu Rabbanan Im Gaoh Yigal, right before ויקרא כ"ז Vayikra
Chaf Zayin in the left-hand margin. And our learning should be for
the תפילה tefillah for the safety of our חיילים Chayalim and חיילות
Chayalot and the swift return of the hostages, speedy end of the
war. All right, so our משנה mishna spoke about is we're dealing
with the issue about אונאה, onaah, it speaks about coins and how
much a coin can be missing because coins were precious value, so
if they're actually missing something they genuinely were worth less. And then
it said that even a coin that was missing a little bit
could be used for to be redeem מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, and
that led the גמרא Gemara to discuss are you redeeming מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni based on the face value of the coin or based
on the actual current value of the coin, which led to a
whole discussion about being פודה מעשר שני podah Maaser Sheni that has
of less of a value of a פרוטה, prutah, and can you
be פודה podah it onto a coin if it's from scratch? If
the coin already was being used for to redeem מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni and there was leftover value you can, חזקיה's Hizkiyah teaching, but
the assertion was was that if it starts with less than if
it's a new coin and the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is less
than a פרוטה, prutah,
you cannot do a redeem it onto the coin. Okay, and now
we are going to wrap that up with actually quoting the פסוק
pasuk on which this is based. So again, about fifteen lines from
the bottom on נ"ג עמוד ב׳, Nun Gimmel amud bet, תנו רבנן
אם גאל יגאל איש ממעשרו, Tanu Rabbanan Im Gaoh Yigal Ish MiMaasro,
if a person redeems from his מעשר, maaser, his מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, ממעשרו, MiMaasro, from his מעשר maaser ולא כל מעשרו, velo kol
maasro, but not all his מעשר, maaser, there's times you cannot redeem
from your מעשר. maaser. What's the case? פרט למעשר שני שאין בו
שוה פרוטה, Prat leMaaser Sheni she'ein bo shaveh prutah, that's coming to
teach you that when it's not worth a פרוטה, prutah, it's not
considered to have value, you can't do this act of redeeming. Of
course, again, it's funny because you can do it when the coin
already has been used in redemption and you have some leftover value,
then you can go ahead and do the redemption even though the
מעשר maaser does not have a פרוטה. prutah. Okay, so what how's
this proving either side? So let's take a look. אתמר, Itmar,
it was taught, רב אמר אין בו, Rav amar ein bo, that
the מעשר maaser you're trying to redeem has less than a פרוטה,
prutah, which is what we've been assuming until now.
רב אסי אמר אין
בחומשו, Rav Asi amar ein bechomsho, no no no, it's a problem
even if the חומש, chomesh, when you redeem your own מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni you have to add a fifth, we'll see later that
the fifth is like a quarter, it means when you add it,
it's a fifth of the total. So if it was worth four
and you add one dollar to it, now it's five dollars, so
the dollar you added is a fifth of the end result of
the total. We would call that a quarter, but that's what the
גמרא Gemara understands the fifth of the תורה Torah to be. So
he says the coin has to be worth four פרוטות prutot so
that the חומש chomesh is a פרוטה. prutah. Not the coin, excuse
me, the food. But if the food is less than four פרוטות,
prutot, so the חומש chomesh isn't a פרוטה, prutah, then you can't
redeem. You can't do a redemption if even the חומש chomesh value
does not have a פרוטה prutah worth of value to be redeemed
on the coin, which is pretty interesting because you would think that
the פרוטה prutah gets wrapped up with the whole thing. So now
you're redeeming I don't know 4.8 פרוטות prutot worth of food, if
you started with you know 3.9 or something, what does it matter?
But somehow this is looking at the פרוטה prutah as a separate
act of redemption somehow, or you're adding
the חומש, chomesh, it's looking at the חומש chomesh as a separate
act of redemption and you're adding the חומש, chomesh, so that חומש,
chomesh, that act of adding, that also has to have a פרוטה
prutah of value. All right, so רב אסי אמר אין בחומשו, Rav
Asi amar ein bechomsho, it's a problem even if the food is
less than four פרוטות, prutot, so that the חומש chomesh doesn't have
a פרוטה, prutah, that also cannot be redeemed. רבי יוחנן אמר אין
בו, רבי שמעון בן לקיש אמר אין בחומשו, Rebbe Yochanan amar ein
bo, Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish amar ein bechomsho, so another debate right
lines up also between רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and רייש לקיש. Resh
Lakish. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this, מעשר שני שאין בו
שוה פרוטה דיו שיאמר הוא וחומשו מחולל על מעות ראשונות. Maaser Sheni
she'ein bo shaveh pruto dayo sheyomar hu vechomsho mechulal al maos rishonos.
So if you have מעשר שני Maaser Sheni that isn't worth a
פרוטה, prutah, it's sufficient that you say דיו, dayo, it's sufficient that
you say he and the fifth
are redeemed on this original money. Now what does this mean, original
money? That's the חזקיה Hizkiyah הלכה. halacha. If you have money that
was already used in redemption and you have some leftover value, then
you can go ahead and do the redemption even though the מעשר
maaser does not have a פרוטה. prutah. Okay, so what how's this
proving either side? So let's take a look.
בשלמא למאן דאמר אין בחומשו, היינו דקתני דיו. Bishlama leman de'amar ein
bechomsho, hayinu diktani dayo. If you say
that it's a problem even if the חומש chomesh doesn't have a
פרוטה, prutah, then we understand what the word means, it's enough, meaning
you've already got some part of the way so you don't have
to worry about the rest. If you've got that the מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni itself... is worth a פרוטה peruta *prutah*,
then it's okay even if the חומש chomesh. *chomesh* is not worth
a פרוטה perutah. *prutah* because at least you have money that was
already used in redemption. So that would be saying the general הלכה
halacha *halacha* is the חומש chomesh *chomesh* has to be worth a
פרוטה perutah, *prutah*, but if the money was already used in redemption,
then as long as the מעשר ma'aser *maiser* is worth a פרוטה
*prutah*, it's okay even if the חומש chomesh. *chomesh* is not. You
understand the דייו *dayo* because you've at least achieved something. The מעשר
ma'aser *maiser* was worth a פרוטה *prutah* even though the חומש chomesh,
*chomesh* was not, and here it's okay because the money was already
used in redemption. But generally you need the חומש chomesh, *chomesh* to
be worth a פרוטה *prutah*. That we can read. אלא *Ella* but
היינו דקתני דייו *hynu dektani dayo*. אף על גב דבדידי אית ביה
*Af al gav de-bedidei it bei*, even though the מעשר ma'aser *maiser*
does have a פרוטה *prutah*, כיון דבחומשיה ליכא שפיר *keivan de-ve-chumshai leika
shapir* that you know even though but okay
so because you know the original value has a פרוטה *prutah*, the
חומש chomesh *chomesh* doesn't have it. That normally would be a problem
but it's alright here. You can do it, it's okay, we can
manage because you know the money was already been used. אלא *Ella*,
למאן דאמר אין בו *leman de-amar ein bo*, מאי mai, דייו *mai
dayo*? But if you say that even the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
*maiser sheini* doesn't have a פרוטה *prutah*'s worth, then it should have
said, מעשר שני ma'aser sheni *maiser sheini* that isn't worth a פרוטה
*prutah* you can redeem it on money that was already used. What's
the דייו *dayo*? דייו *dayo* sounds like you've accomplished something but not
the whole thing. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concedes קשיא *kasha*. Okay,
that's difficult. The word דייו *dayo* is difficult. But anyway, that is
the debate whether everybody agrees once the money was already used you
don't need the פרוטה *prutah*, but if the money wasn't used yet,
it's empty money as it were, then the debate is do you
need the מעשר ma'aser *maiser* to be worth a פרוטה *prutah* or
do you even need the חומש chomesh *chomesh* to be worth a
פרוטה *prutah*? Okay. איבעיא להו iba'ya lehu, *ibaya lehu*, they asked the
question: חומשא מלגאו או חומשא מלבר milbar. *Chumsha mi-legav o chumsha mi-lebar*?
So I already addressed this. Is the חומש chomesh? *chomesh* from the
inside or from the outside? Meaning do
you when you go ahead and you figure out the fifth, do
you do it from the מלגאו *mi-legav*, meaning you look at your
base. If you have something worth twenty, what's a fifth of twenty?
Four. So the חומש chomesh *chomesh* would be four. That's looking at
it from the inside, before you add. You start from the core
before the חומש chomesh. *chomesh* has added. That's
מלגאו *mi-legav*. Or do you say מלבר *mi-lebar*? From the outside. After
you've added the fifth, then it's a fifth of the total. That
would be a quarter. If you would start with twenty you would
add five, so in the end you'd have twenty-five and the five
would be a fifth of the outside of the total. All right,
so which way is it? אמר רבינא amar Ravina, תא שמע ta
shma, *Amar Ravina tashma*, come here. הבעלים אומרים בעשרים וכל אדם בעשרים
*Habe'alim omrim be-esrim ve-chol adam be-esrim*. So let's say the you know
if you've sanctified an object and to the בית המקדש beit hamikdash
*Beis Hamikdash* and now you want to redeem it and you want
to take it back. You sanctified your car. But the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* wants money. So are you going to redeem
your car and give the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* money
or is somebody else going to redeem it?
So if you redeem it you add a חומש chomesh. *chomesh*. So
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* has an auction. So you
say you'll give twenty for it.
Okay, הבעלים אומרים בעשרים וכל אדם בעשרים *Habe'alim omrim be-esrim ve-chol adam
be-esrim*, and somebody else says twenty. הבעלים קודמין מפני שהם מוסיפין חומש
chomesh *Habe'alim kodmin mipnei she-mosifin chomesh*. So the בעלים be'alim *be'alim* have
the right to redeem it because they add a חומש chomesh *chomesh*.
אמר אחד הרי עלי בעשרים ואחד *Amar echad harei alai be-esrim ve-echad*.
Now the owners say I'll pay twenty to get that car back
and somebody else says I'll pay twenty-one. הבעלים נותנין עשרים ושש *Habe'alim
nosnin esrim ve-sheish*. The owners pay twenty-six. Why twenty-six?
Because since they're going to add a חומש chomesh, *chomesh*, they're so
anyway what's clear here, let's just say from the outset is that
the fifth of twenty is five, okay? Five is what is being
added for the בעלים *be'alim*'s חומש chomesh *chomesh*, which shows that it
is מלבר *mi-lebar*, that we consider it would be a quarter of
twenty which is five, twenty-five, so the five is now a fifth
of the total result at the end, twenty-five. So that's מלבר *mi-lebar*,
okay? So when the fifth of the תורה Torah *Torah* is a
fifth after you add it, which is a quarter from where you're
starting. That's proving our point. Now let's explain what the meaning of
this ברייתא braisa *braisa* is. So
the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* is going to favor the owners
because their twenty plus five, twenty-five is going to be higher than
the other guy's twenty-one. But the owners really now get like the
worst of both worlds because even though so the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash*, well not the worst, but the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is
going to give it to them, but they can't allow the owners
to pay less than the value that somebody else assigned to it.
So therefore the owners are going to get the right to do
it but at the other person's twenty-one, but they have to add
five. Now they're not adding a fifth, now they're adding a fifth
to the twenty-one, they're adding a fifth to the twenty because really
they're redeeming it at twenty and they're doing twenty-five, but in order
that they shouldn't be paying less than the base amount of the
other person, they throwing in an extra one. That's the principle of
this ברייתא. braisa. Okay, now נותן עשרים ושש. noten esrim veshesh. עשרים
ושתיים, esrim veshtayim, somebody else says 22, so הבעלים נותן עשרים ושבע,
habe'alim noten esrim vesheva, so the owners get it because their 20
plus five is 25 is bigger than 22, but in order that
they shouldn't be paying less for a base they add another two
and 27. The owners have to know this going in so they
don't wind up paying more than they are ready to pay. עשרים
ושלוש, esrim veshalosh, הבעלים נותן עשרים ושמונה. habe'alim noten esrim veshmona. עשרים
וארבע, esrim ve'arba, הבעלים נותן עשרים ותשע. habe'alim noten esrim vetisha. Keeps
on going this way. Guy says 24, owners say 20, their 25
is more than 24, so they pay 25 plus the extra four,
29. עשרים וחמש, esrim vechamish, now let's say somebody else has 25.
הבעלים נותן שלושים. habe'alim noten shloshim.
They pay 30. לפי lefi
okay...
שאין מוסיפין חומש על עילויו של זה she'ein mosifin chomesh al iluyo
shel zeh because they don't pay, this is what I said before,
they don't pay their fifth on the guy's outbidding. They're not paying
a fifth on 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. They're paying a fifth
on their bid. Okay, so they fit 20, a fifth on their
bid makes it 25 and then, but they're adding the other guy's
עילויא, iluyo, his overbid, then they add it to their total. Now
the obvious question here is the last case, 30. That's a case,
that doesn't seem fair. If this guy said 25 as a base
and the בעלים said 20 plus their fifth makes it 25, why
do you give it to the owners and force them to pay
30? The other guy's base of 25 should take precedence over the
owner's base of 20 plus the fifth of the חומש. chomesh So
the גמרא Gemara over there, you know, in where this is from
over in ערכין, Erchin, asks this question, but that's not our interest
right now. Okay, so what does the גמרא Gemara say? שמע מינה
חומש מלבר שמע מינה. shma mina chomesh milbar shma mina. So it's
very clear the חומש is after you're done. That is a good
proof. It was we would call it a quarter of what you
started with. כתנאי, ketannai, this question about, you know, is a debate
of תנאי. tannai. ויסף חמישיתו עליו, veyasaf chamishito alav,
you should add the fifth, שהו וחומשו חמישה דברי רבי יאשיה. shehu
vechomsho chamisha divrei Rabbi Yoshiya.
So Rabbi Yoshiya says once you add it, you have a total
of five. So you start with four, you add one, you have
a total of five. That's מלבר. רבי יונתן אומר חמישיתו חומשו של
קרן. Rabbi Yonatan omer chamishito chomsho shel keren. No, a fifth of
what you started with. But the principle is it is a fifth
of the end, a quarter of what you started with. Alright, איבעיא
להו, now they ask the question. And now we're going to have
fun questions about חומש. חומש מעכב או אין חומש מעכב? chomesh me'akev
o ein chomesh me'akev?
Does the חומש, if you don't give the חומש, does it prevent
the פדיון pidyon from working? Okay, now if you redeemed your מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni. out of ירושלים Yerushalayim and it was worth 20
and you redeemed it on 20 and not on 25, can you
go ahead and eat your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni out of ירושלים?
Yerushalayim? Did the מעשר ma'aser, actually get redeemed or not? Okay, so
let's take a look.
ארבע בארבע, arba be'arba,
how do you conceptualize it? Do you say ארבע בארבע פריק? arba
be'arba parik? That basically when the תורה Torah says you redeem it
and add a fifth, here's what the תורה Torah say: this is
worth four, you do one, the way you redeem it is you
redeem it on four. Now you've redeemed your מעשר שני. maaser sheni
ואכינפשיה מוסיף חומש ve'achinafshei mosif chomesh and then on top of that
you add a fifth. But the basic act of redemption is on
its value. If that's true, the fifth is something you have to
do but the מעשר ma'aser got redeemed even without adding the fifth.
אלמא חומש לא מעכב, alma chomesh lo me'akev,
which would lead to the conclusion that the חומש is not מעכב.
me'akev. או דילמא, o dilma, or you'd say ארבע בחמישה פריק וחומש
מעכב. arba bachamisha parik vechomesh me'akev.
Or no, what the תורה Torah is telling you is if you
want to redeem four, you have to redeem it on five. And
if you're redeeming it on four, you're not redeeming it at the
right value and therefore the פדיון pidyon doesn't work. So that's a
very beautiful conceptual way of asking it. Is it fundamentally you do
it on the value plus you add a חומש and then the
פדיון pidyon works without the חומש? Or do you do it with
the total, you know, you redeem four on five? How do you
think about it? You can think about what the גמרא Gemara before
about whether the חומש had to be worth a פרוטה could be
a little bit tied into whether you see it as a separate
thing or as part of the same thing. Anyway, let's see how
the גמרא Gemara answers.
אמר רבינא, Ravina תא שמע, come and hear. הדמאי אין לו חומש
ואין לו ביעור. hadmai ein lo chomesh ve'ein lo biur. That if
you have דמאי, dmai, you know, מעשר ma'aser, from grain of an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, so it's מעשר שני maaser sheni
of
דמאי, dmai, you don't know if the עם הארץ am ha'aretz took
it or not, so דרבנן, derabbanan, דאורייתא de'oraita you could assume he
did, דרבנן derabbanan you have to take it again.
So you don't add a fifth. And also you don't have ביעור.
biur. If it's the third year and you have to get rid
of all the מעשר maiser. from your home, you don't have to
do it to דמאי. dmai. Because again דאורייתא de'oraita you assume it
was taken. הקרן יש לו. hakaren yesh lo. Okay, fine, but you
obviously still have to redeem it based on the principal amount. You
still have to redeem it. מעשר שני ma'aser sheni of דמאי, demai,
but you just don't add a fifth. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's
the logic to say that you would have to do the קרן
keren but not the דמאי, demai, but not the fifth? How do
you conceptualize why חזל Chazal would have split the two?
קרן דמעכב בדאורייתא איתא בדרבנן חומש דלא מעכב בדאורייתא ליתא בדרבנן. Keren
d'me'akeiv b'de'oraita ita b'de-rabbanan chomesh d'lo me'akeiv b'de'oraita leita b'de-rabbanan. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so רבינא Ravina: says, look, if דמאי demai is
an addition, but the fundamental redemption is on the value, and the
דמאי demai is something you do in addition but it doesn't prevent
the redemption from happening, then you understand why they said, okay, by
דמאי demai you don't have to worry about it, we'll just focus
on the core act of redemption, the thing that is מעכב דאורייתא,
me'akeiv de'oraita, the equal value. The extra thing you're supposed to do,
since this is only דמאי, demai, we don't demand that of you.
But if you think that in the תורה Torah the דמאי demai
is מעכב me'akeiv and it's all
one big you know one bundle act, you redeem four on five,
then why even if it's דרבנן de-rabbanan and it's דמאי, demai, why
would they change? If the תורה says you redeem four on five,
why would the רבנן Rabbanan say you redeem four on four? Doesn't
make any sense. That's a pretty good proof. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says לימא כתנאי, Leima ketannai, maybe it's a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. It seems to accept that proof, but maybe still other תנאים
Tannaim debate it. נתן את הקרן ולא נתן את החומש. Natan et
hakeren v'lo natan et hachomesh. Let's say somebody
gave
the principal and he did not give you know the חומש.
So let's take a look.
נתן את הקרן ולא נתן את החומש. Natan et hakeren v'lo natan
et hachomesh. רבי אליעזר אומר יאכל, Rabbi Eliezer omer yochal, you can
go ahead and eat the מעשר שני even without giving the fifth.
רבי יהושע אומר לא יאכל, Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo yochal, you can't
eat it. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, says רבי, Rabbi, נראין דברי רבי
אליעזר בשבת ודברי רבי יהושע בחול. Nirim divrei Rabbi Eliezer b'Shabbat v'divrei
Rabbi Yehoshua b'chol. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer makes sense on שבת Shabbat
because then we'll go easier on you and let you go ahead
and eat it because you know you need food for שבת, Shabbat,
so we'll allow that to work. But רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua on
a normal weekday, no, it won't work unless you add the fifth.
Now that's interesting. That sounds like it's a secondary concern for רבי.
Rabbi. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מדאמר נראין דברי רבי
אליעזר בשבת, Mide'amar nirin divrei Rabbi Eliezer b'Shabbat, since he
says רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position makes sense on שבת, Shabbat, מכלל
דפליגי אפילו בחול, mikhlal d'pligi afilu b'chol, it sounds like you know
the debate is both שבת Shabbat and the weekday and he's splitting
the vote, רבי. Rabbi. מדאמר נראין דברי רבי יהושע בחול, Mide'amar nirin
divrei Rabbi Yehoshua b'chol, since he says רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua's position
makes sense in a weekday, מכלל דפליגי אפילו בשבת, mikhlal d'pligi afilu
b'Shabbat, it shows that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua disagrees even on שבת.
Shabbat. Right, since רבי Rabbi is splitting the vote, it seems that
between רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, they're both
saying, you know, one is saying it never works without adding the
fifth, not on שבת, Shabbat, not on the weekday, and the other
says it always works without adding the fifth, whether שבת, Shabbat, whether
weekday, and רבי Rabbi is splitting the vote. So before we get
to רבי, Rabbi, if they those two are taking opposite positions and
they don't distinguish שבת Shabbat or weekday, what would be the logic
to explain the debate? So the גמרא Gemara says let's say this
is the issue. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, Mai lav beha kamifligi, let's
say this is what they argue about? מאי לאו בהא סברא קמיפלגי?
Mai lav beha sevara kamifligi? רבי אליעזר סבר חומש לא מעכב, Rabbi
Eliezer savar chomesh lo me'akeiv, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says whether שבת,
Shabbat, whether weekday, it works if you don't add a fifth. So
clearly he's saying the fifth is not מעכב. me'akeiv. That's very clear.
So that's another proof to the idea that the fifth is not
מעכב. me'akeiv. How about רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Let's take a look.
ורבי יהושע סבר חומש מעכב, V'Rabbi Yehoshua savar chomesh me'akeiv, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says whether שבת Shabbat or weekday, you can't eat it
if you don't add the fifth. So on the face of it,
that sounds like the fifth is מעכב. me'akeiv.
But רבי Rabbi is already pointing to us to a possibility that
there might be something else going on here. So let's take a
look. אמר רב פפא לא, Amar Rav Pappa lo, no, you do
not have to say that that's a debate. דכולי עלמא חומש לא
מעכב, Dekulei alma chomesh lo me'akeiv, everybody could hold the fifth is
not מעכב. me'akeiv. That's clearly true from רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says without the fifth you can still eat it.
But even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua could hold that in principle. והכא
בחיישינן לפשיעותא קמיפלגי, V'hacha b'chashinan l'fshiyuta kamifligi,
the question is at a rabbinic level. דאורייתא, de'oraita, the fifth is
not מעכב. me'akeiv. At a rabbinic level, if you didn't add the
fifth, do we let you go ahead and eat it? Or דרבנן
de-rabbanan we say it hasn't worked, at least at a דרבנן de-rabbanan
level. Why should we say it doesn't work? Because we're afraid you'll
be negligent. If there's no consequences, if you can go ahead and
go ahead and eat it without adding the fifth, you'll say yeah,
yeah, yeah, I'll get to the fifth, and you'll never get to
it. The only way we're going to get you to do the
fifth is if we tell you that you can't eat it until
you do it. But it's purely rabbinic.
So רבי, Rabbi, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says you can
go ahead and eat it, so clearly for him it's not מעכב.
me'akeiv. But even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you can't eat it,
that could just be דרבנן de-rabbanan in order to make sure you
do it. וחיישינן לפשיעותא קמיפלגי, V'chashinan l'fshiyuta kamifligi, מר סבר חיישינן לפשיעותא,
Mar savar chashinan l'fshiyuta,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says we're concerned you'll be negligent, ומר סבר
לא חיישינן לפשיעותא, u-mar savar lo chashinan l'fshiyuta,
and by the way, that explains that works extremely well with רבי
Rabbi's splitting of the vote. 'cause רבי *Rebbe*'s splitting of the vote
of שבת *Shabbos* and weekdays shows that it's purely a secondary rabbinic
concern. So רבי *Rebbe* says, you know what, it makes sense to
be strict on you and not let you eat it during the
weekday because we don't want you to be negligent, but on שבת
*Shabbos*, for the sake of having food on שבת *Shabbos*, we'll go
easy and we'll let you eat it. So that can only make
sense if it's a secondary concern. So the easiest way to learn
it is everybody agrees in principle it works, and the question is
do we have this other safeguard to not let you eat it,
to not make you be negligent. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן הכל מודים
בהקדש שחילל הוא וגזברין תובעין אותו בשוק *Amar Rabbi Yochanan hakol modim
b'hektesh shechilel hov v'gizbarin tovin oso b'shuk*. Everybody,
since the concern is negligence, we can have this debate by do
we let you eat it when we're dealing with מעשר *Maaser*? Because
מעשר *Maaser*, nobody is going to come and make sure that you
cough up the fifth. So there we could have the position of
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* that says I don't want you to do
it, I'm not going to let you eat it until you add
the fifth.
But when it comes to הקדש hekdesh, *Hektesh*, you sanctify your car,
he says, and now you gotta redeem it and add a fifth,
you gotta your twenty plus your plus your five. So in that
case he says even if you just did the twenty, you can
go ahead and drive your car and go ahead and back and
and now start using it, and we'll let you use it because
we're not afraid you're going to forget to add the extra five.
You know why? 'Cause the IRS, the treasurer of the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash*, they're going to come after you and make sure you
pay it. There's somebody that's going to demand the payment. So everybody,
even רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* would not make a safeguard there 'cause
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is going to demand their money. הכל
מודים בהקדש שחילל הוא וגזברין תובעין אותו בשוק *Hakol modim b'hektesh shechilel
hov v'gizbarin tovin oso b'shuk*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: ובהקדש לא פליגי *U'v'hektesh lo pligi*? Is that really true they
don't argue by something you sanctify to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*?
והתניא *V'hatanya*, didn't we teach in a ברייתא *braisa*: נתן את הקרן
ולא נתן את החומש *Nasan es hakeren v'lo nasan es hachomesh*, let's
say somebody gave the principal and didn't add the fifth, רבי אליעזר
אומר חילל וחכמים אומרים לא חילל *Rabbi Eliezer omer chilel v'Chachamim omrim
lo chilel*, it didn't work. Okay, now what are we talking about,
הקדש Hekdesh? *Hektesh* or מעשר *Maaser*? So let's take a look at
similar to the debate before, except here it's רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
and the חכמים *Chachamim*. So אמר רבי נירין דברי רבי אליעזר בהקדש
ודברי חכמים במעשר *Amar Rebbe nirin divrei Rabbi Eliezer b'hektesh v'divrei Chachamim
b'maaser*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says, so the רבי *Rebbe* split the
vote. You know, he says what רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* makes sense
that it works, makes sense by הקדש Hekdesh? *Hektesh* 'cause הקדש Hekdesh.
*Hektesh* will eventually get their money. The חכמים *Chachamim* that say it
doesn't work, makes sense by מעשר *Maaser*. We're not going to let
you do it because we're going to make a safeguard because we
want to make sure that you're not negligent. So there you actually
see that the debate presumably the חכמים *Chachamim* here is the רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* whatever, it seems like they're debating both הקדש Hekdesh
*Hektesh* and מעשר *Maaser*. Okay, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מדיקאמר נירין דברי רבי אליעזר בהקדש
*Mi d'ka amar nirin divrei Rabbi Eliezer b'hektesh*, since רבי *Rebbe* says
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s position that it works makes sense by הקדש
Hekdesh? *Hektesh*, מכלל דפליגי אפילו במעשר *miklal d'pligi afilu b'maaser*. It sounds
like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says I'm fine whether הקדש Hekdesh? *Hektesh*
or מעשר *Maaser*. And we saw from before that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* was fine by מעשר *Maaser*. He doesn't need to make a
safeguard and he says it works even if you don't add a
חומש *chomesh*. מדיקאמרי נירין דברי חכמים במעשר *Mi d'ka amri nirin divrei
Chachamim b'maaser*, and since רבי *Rebbe* says it makes sense what the
חכמים *Chachamim* say by מעשר *Maaser*, מכלל *miklal* from that we can
infer that it doesn't work because מעשר *Maaser* won't get its money.
מכלל דאינהו פליגי אפילו בהקדש *miklal d'inhu pligi afilu b'hektesh*, the חכמים
*Chachamim* say it doesn't work even by הקדש Hekdesh *Hektesh*. רבי *Rebbe*
is splitting the vote. But רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is saying I
don't make a safeguard by הקדש hekdesh. *Hektesh* or מעשר *Maaser*, I
let it work, I am not concerned, they'll get their money. And
the חכמים *Chachamim* presumably slash רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* saying whether by
מעשר *Maaser* or by הקדש hekdesh, *Hektesh*, I'm going to say it's
not going to work, I'm not going to be because I'm going
to make a safeguard, I want to make sure they get their
money even by הקדש hekdesh *Hektesh*. And it's only רבי *Rebbe* who
splits the vote and says you know by הקדש *Hektesh* maybe we
don't need a safeguard. So that goes against the argument that everybody
agrees by הקדש *Hektesh*. מכלל דאינהו פליגי אפילו בהקדש *Miklal d'inhu pligi
afilu b'hektesh*, אלא אי איתמר הכי *ela iy itmar hachi*. Fine. If
the statement by רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* was said that everybody agrees,
it was said in the following way: not that everybody agrees by
הקדש *Hektesh*, clearly the רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* position says even by
הקדש *Hektesh* we make a safeguard, but when you have both factors
combined, everybody agrees. הכי קאיתמר *Hachi ka itmar*: אמר רבי יוחנן הכל
מודים בשבת בהקדש שחילל *Amar Rabbi Yochanan hakol modim b'Shabbos b'hektesh shechilel*.
Everybody agrees that if you're doing it for שבת *Shabbos* and it's
הקדש *Hektesh*, then it works. A, because it's הקדש *Hektesh* there's less
of a need of a safeguard, and B, because it's שבת *Shabbos*
there's more of a reason to go easy on you so you
have food for שבת *Shabbos*. חדא דכתיב וקראת לשבת עונג *Chada d'chesiv
v'karasa l'Shabbos Oneg*, you want to have good food for שבת *Shabbos*.
ועוד הוא וגזברין תובעין אותו בשוק *V'od hov v'gizbarin tovin oso b'shuk*.
All right. Very nice. So that was the question of whether the
fifth is מעכב *m'akev* and we basically come to the principle that
to the conclusion that fundamentally it is not.
Is questions whether though we make a safeguard at a דרבנן *derabbanan*
level. Okay. Now, by the way, an interesting תוספות *Tosafos* to the
top of the דף *daf* here, או דילמא ארבעה בה' *o dilma
arbaa beheh*. תוספות *Tosafos* asks a question: The idea that the fifth
is מעכב *me'akev* is because what we would be saying is that
what the תורה *Torah* is saying is, if you redeem four, four
has to be redeemed on five. But תוספות *Tosafos* says one minute,
the principle is that בדיעבד *bedieved* when you redeem מעשר *ma'aser* or
הקדש *hekdesh* even on less than its value, בדיעבד *bedieved* it works.
If I took מעשר *ma'aser* worth four and I redeemed it on
three, בדיעבד—it's not—I'm not allowed to, but בדיעבד *bedieved* that would work.
So even if the תורה *Torah* said redeem four on five, why
should it be מעכב *me'akev*? Let's take a look at that תוספות
*Tosafos*. Top תוספות *Tosafos*. ואם תאמר *ve'im tomar* says תוספות *Tosafos*, והלא
בהקדש שוה מנה שחיללו על שוה פרוטה מחולל *vehalo behekdesh shoveh maneh
shechilalo al shoveh prutah mecholal*, ומסתמא הוא הדין במעשר *umistama hu hadin
bema'aser*. By הקדש *hekdesh* when you do a thousand dollars on a
dollar, on a penny, it works, and presumably by מעשר *ma'aser* as
well, we don't know proof but presumably. ויש לומר דוקא אם אמר
הוא וחומשו מחולל על פרוטה מהני *veyesh lomar davka im amar hu
vechumsho mecholal al prutah mahani*. תוספות *Tosafos* says you're right, if you
said look, it and its פרוטה *prutah*, the five dollar value here
I am redeeming on one dollar, that would work. Okay, yes, it
does work בדיעבד *bedieved* if you do it on less than its
value. אבל כי לא מזכיר בהדיא החומש למהני *aval ki lo mazkir
behedya hachomesh lamahani*. But if you don't say that, it doesn't work.
If you say I am redeeming this four on four and you
didn't mention, meaning the basis you have to redeem the four on
the five. You can say you're doing it on less and then
it'll work, but if you're not trying to do it on less,
you're trying to do it the right way, then four on four
won't work because it has to be four on the four plus
the חומש *chomesh*. Okay, that was an interesting little side point. Back
to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Okay. Now we're going to ask some other questions about חומש *chomesh*
and about the חומש *chomesh*'s connection to the base. אמר רמי בר
חמא הרי אמרו *amar Rami bar Chama harei amru*. About four or
five lines before the lines get wide. הקדש אינו מתחלל על קרקע
*hekdesh eino mischallel al karka*. You can't redeem הקדש *hekdesh* on land.
דרחמנא אמר ונתן הכסף וקם לו *derachmana amar venasan hakesef vekam lo*,
because the תורה *Torah* says you shall give the money and it
shall be, you know, established for you or whatever, the property shall
become yours, so you redeem it onto money. The problem is, by
the way, there's no פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that actually says that, but
whatever. Okay. הקדש *hekdesh* cannot be redeemed—has to be redeemed on chattel,
can't be redeemed on land. חומשו מהו שיתחלל על קרקע *chumsho mahu
sheyischallel al karka*? How about the חומש *chomesh*? Does the חומש *chomesh*
have to be redeemed on chattel or can the חומש *chomesh* also
be redeemed on land? תרומה teruma אינה משתלמת אלא מן החולין *terumah
einah mishtalemes ela min hachullin*. Here's הלכות *halachos* that apply to the
principle of a lot of things and we want to know does
it also apply to the fifth. If somebody eats תרומה teruma. *terumah*
בשוגג b'shogeg, *beshogeg*, a זר *zar*, a non-כהן kohen, *kohen*, he has
to give back food and the food becomes of חולין chulin. *chullin*,
non-תרומה teruma *terumah* food, and that becomes תרומה teruma. *terumah*. Okay, that's
the הלכה halacha *halacha*. You give the food and the food then
automatically becomes תרומה teruma *terumah*. דרחמנא אמר ונתן לכהן את הקדש *derachmana
amar venasan lakohen es hakodesh*, you give the כהן kohen, *kohen* the
holy thing, דבר הראוי להיות קודש *davar harauy lihyos kodesh*, something that
can be קודש *kodesh* that becomes תרומה teruma *terumah*. חומשו מהו שישתלם
שלא מן החולין *chumsho mahu sheyishtalem shelo min hachullin*? How about the
חומש *chomesh*? Can you pay it not from חולין chulin. *chullin*? Not
from חולין chulin *chullin* here doesn't mean from הקדש *hekdesh*, but can
you give like the חומש *chomesh* of the תרומה teruma *terumah* you
ate בשוגג b'shogeg, *beshogeg*, can you give a car, can you give
a ten dollar bill, or does it have to be something that
can transfer into תרומה teruma, *terumah*? Is food that can transfer into
תרומה teruma. *terumah*? Okay, similar question, how much is it all one
bundle or not? We might have concluded that in the act of
redemption they're separate, four on four plus one, not four on five,
but how much is that plus one patterned after the original or
is it a completely separate? מעשר אין מתחלל על
אסימון *ma'aser ein mischallel al asimon*. מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni* cannot be
redeemed on an אסימון *asimon*, on a coin that doesn't have a
stamped image. דרחמנא אמר וצרת הכסף בידך לרבות כל דבר שיש לו
צורה *derachmana amar vezarta hakesef beyadecha lerabbos kol davar sheyesh lo tzurah*.
You shall bind the money in your hand to include everything that
has an image type of stamped on it. Okay. It can't just
be, you know, a piece of metal. חומשו מהו שיתחלל על אסימון
*chumsho mahu sheyischallel al asimon*? How about the חומש *chomesh* of מעשר
*ma'aser*? Does that have to be on a similar type of money
or can that also be on אסימון *asimon*, unstamped coins? Okay, so
all very interesting questions, great questions. איגלגל מילתא ומטא לקמיה דרבא *igalgul
milsa umata likamei deRava*. So the matter rolled around, meaning people were
discussing it and finally it came to רבא *Rava*. אמר להו אמר
קרא amar kra עליו *amar lehu amar kra alav*. All the פסוקים
pesukim, *pesukim* by חומש *chomesh* says ואסף חמישיתו עליו chamishito alav. *ve'asaf
chamishiso alav*, you shall add its fifth on it. So עליו *alav*
means לרבות חומשו כמותו chomsho k'moso *lerabbos chumsho kemoso*, that it has
to be just like it. So, you know, תוספות *Tosafos* points out
it's not just like it, it's not מעכב *me'akev*, but the nature
of the object has to be similar to the object that you're
doing the original redemption of. Okay. אמר רבינא אף אנן נמי תנינא
*amar Ravina af anan nami tanina*. הגונב תרומה teruma ולא אכלה achla,
משלם תשלומי כפל דמי תרומה. m'shaleim tashlumei khefel d'mei teruma. If somebody
stole תרומה teruma and didn't eat it, and then when you pay
back, you pay double. How do you figure out the double? The
double is the market value of the תרומה. teruma The market value
of the תרומה teruma. is less than had it not been תרומה.
teruma, If I stole, if a bushel of grain, I don't know,
a box of apples was worth ten dollars, then a box of
תרומה teruma. apples might only be worth five dollars. Why? Because only
כהנים kohanim can eat it, only when they're טהור. tahor. If the
תרומה teruma. becomes טמא, tamei, they can't eat it. So maybe it's
only worth three dollars. So if I stole a box of תרומה
teruma apples from a כהן, if the apples are around fine, I
give him back the apples, what's the כפל? khefel? Whatever the, not
the ten dollars that they would go for if they were not
תרומה, teruma but the five dollars that they're going for, that they
would go for because they are תרומה. terumah So that's משלם תשלומי
כפל khefel, דמי תרומה. terumah אכלה, now if the person ate it,
okay, and בשוגג, beshogeg so now the הלכה halacha is that he
still has to pay כפל, khefel, but for his eating, he pays
the principle plus a, plus a fifth.
משלם שני קרניים וחומש. m'shaleim shnei karnoim v'chomesh. He pays two principles
and a fifth, meaning the two principles is like קרן וכפל, keren
v'khefel, but we'll see what this means. קרן וחומש מן החולין. keren
v'chomesh min ha-chulin. So for the apples that were eaten, that were,
and you know he ate this box of תרומה terumah, apples, so
now בשוגג, beshogeg? so now his תרומה terumah paying back is first
you have to give back a box of apples. Okay? We don't
ask about market value, the הלכה halacha of תרומה terumah is give
back similar food and that's now going to become תרומה. terumah. So
you give back a box of apples. Okay? It might have to
cost you ten dollars because you had to buy it at market
value unless you had it in your own backyard, right? And it
has to be חולין. So you now have bought a ten dollar
bag of market box of apples, you give it back to the
כהן, they become תרומה, terumah. and then you also give a fifth
of that back from the חולין. So if that was ten apples,
you give an additional, well let's say eight apples, you give an
additional two apples for your חומש. Okay, so that's the principle plus
a חומש you give back in apples and they become תרומה. terumah
קרן
וחומש
מן החולין, keren v'chomesh min ha-chulin, so קרן keren and the חומש
from חולין meaning from the apples, from the food that's now going
to become תרומה. terumah וקרן דמי תרומה, v'keren d'mei teruma, the other,
so that's your first, your principle plus the fifth. Now you also
owe another principle amount for כפל, but that goes back to the
previous rule that you don't look at it as a box of
apples or whatever, you ask what the market value is. Oh, market
value was only five. So for that you give five. Okay, so
you give a box of apples plus twenty percent more apples or
twenty-five percent more apples, whatever, twenty percent of the end. Okay? Plus
the market value of a box of תרומה terumah apples. Anyway, what
do you see from all of this? That when you're paying back
the חומש, you're paying it back from apples. שמע מינה, shma mina,
says the גמרא Gemara top of דף נ"ד עמוד ב', daf nun
daled amud beis, from here we can hear חומשו כמותו that the
חומש is just like it in terms of the object. שמע מינה,
shma mina, that is a good proof.
Okay, that's a nice answer and presumably if it's true about תרומה
terumah, it's true about the other things as well. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, גבי גזל כתיב, gabei gezel kesiv, by גזל, gezel, when somebody
goes ahead and, you know, swears falsely, that he, he, you said
you stole something from me and he says no I didn't, takes
an oath and then he admits he was lying, he brings a
קורבן אשם korban asham and he also gives the principle plus a
fifth. So גבי גזל כתיב וחמישיתיו יוסף עליו, gabei gezel kesiv v'chamishisav
yoseif alav, the fifths in plural he shall add on it. דתנן,
d'tnan, נתן לו את הקרן ונשבע לו על החומש, nasan lo es
ha-keren v'nishba lo al ha-chomesh,
if somebody, so the guy swore falsely and then he admitted it,
so he gave back the principle, let's say, let's say it was
forty, he gave back forty plus the fifth, another ten, right remember
that's how we consider to be a fifth. Okay? נתן לו את
הקרן, nasan lo es ha-keren, I'm sorry, let's read that again. נתן
לו את הקרן, nasan lo es ha-keren, he gave him the forty,
ונשבע לו על החומש, v'nishba lo al ha-chomesh, and then he didn't
get, give back the fifth, he didn't give back the other ten
he owed, and then the guy said where's the ten you owe
me for the fifth of that thing you swore falsely about? And
he says I already paid it to you. He says no you
didn't. He says swear to me, he says fine, he swore him.
So he swore to him falsely now on the fifth. So ונשבע
לו על החומש הרי זה מוסיף חומש על חומש. v'nishba lo al
ha-chomesh harei zeh mosif chomesh al chomesh. So now he admits it.
So now he gives the ten that he owed which was the
fifth and now he has to give a fifth on that, which
would be two and a half.
Okay? So עד שיתמעט הקרן פחות משווה פרוטה, ad she-yismaet ha-keren pachus
mi-shaveh pruta, keeps on going and going. If he keeps on giving
back the principle and then denying the fifth and then swearing and
then admitting and then swearing again on the other fifth and the
next fifth, he will keep on having to bring another קורבן korban
and having to give another. another fifth on all of the fifths,
עד ad where were
we, עד שימעט הקרן פחות משוה פרוטה ad sheyisma'et hakeren pachos mishve
perutah until the קרן keren the principal, meaning the amount he's swearing
on, it could be the fifth of the fifth of the fifth,
but the amount that he's now swearing falsely on is less than
a פרוטה. But as long as that amount is more than a
פרוטה, this הלכה halacha keeps on applying. What's the פשט pshat about
all of this? That the principle of swearing falsely and adding a
fifth applies not only to the original principal, but even to the
fifth that gets added.
So it's indicated by the פסוקים, pesukim because the פסוקים pesukim say
חמישיתיו chamishitav in the plural, your fifths, plus it's explicitly taught
in the משנה mishna that you can have a fifth on a
fifth. גבי תרומה כתיב איש כי יאכל קדש בשגגה ויסף חמשיתו עליו.
gabei terumah ktiv ish ki yochal kodesh bishgaga veyasaf chamishito alav.
By תרומה Terumah it says when you eat תרומה Terumah בשוגג you
add its fifth in the singular, not fifths. So that might have
indicated you don't do a fifth on a fifth by תרומה, Terumah
but nevertheless, the הלכה halacha is you do. ותנן, utnan, but the
משנה mishna teaches: האוכל תרומה בשוגג משלם קרן וחומש. ha'ochel terumah bishgaga
meshalem keren vechomesh.
If you eat תרומה Terumah by accident, you pay, you know, the
principal, the box of apples plus the extra fifth, two more apples,
אחד האוכל ואחד השותה ואחד הסך, echad ha'ochel ve'echad hashotah ve'echad hasach,
whether you eat or drink תרומה Terumah. or even anoint it onto
your skin, אחד תרומה
טהורה ואחד תרומה טמאה משלם חומשה, echad terumah tehorah ve'echad terumah teme'ah
meshalem chomshah,
you pay it and the fifth, וחומשא דחומשא, vechumsha dechumsha,
a fifth of a fifth. So what happens if the fifth that
you were adding, the extra two apples, you know, you went ahead
and then you ate them בשוגג? So then you would now add
a fifth on the fifth and you would do that as well.
So even though the פסוקים pesukim say only fifth in singular, the
הלכה halacha? is that this idea of adding a fifth applies even
to the fifth of the fifth if that situation ever occurs.
That's by תרומה. Terumah So we know by- what do you call
it? We know by גזל gezel and we know by
תרומה. Terumah. ואילו גבי מעשר לא מכתב כתיב ולא משנה תנא, ve'ilu
gabei ma'aser lo michtav ktiv velo mishnah tana,
it's not any פסוק pasuk that hints to the idea that there's
a fifth on a fifth. Right? By מעשר שני you redeemed your
מעשר, you added a fifth, so you redeemed your מעשר on forty
plus you added ten, and now you want to redeem what you've
redeemed and you want to redeem that fifth and transfer it onto
other money. Do you go ahead and on a fifth on the
fifth? So there's no פסוק pasuk that speaks about fifths in the
plural that would hint to the idea of a fifth and a
fifth. There's no משנה mishna that teaches that there's a fifth of
a fifth by
מעשר, ולא איבעיא איבעיא לן velo ibaya iba'ya lan and we never
thought and we never asked the question to us it was always
taken obvious. Nothing teaches it, so it doesn't apply. It only applies
when you redeem from the original fruit, not when you redeem from
the redeemed things. From the redeemed stuff you do not add a
fifth on a fifth. Okay. גבי הקדש
כתיב
ואם המקדיש יגאל את ביתו ויסף חמישית כסף ערכך עליו. gabei hekdesh
ktiv ve'im hamakdish yigal et beito veyasaf chamishit kesef erchecha alav. Okay,
when a person redeems his house, he adds the fifth of the
value. So that says חמישית. chamishit. It doesn't say plural
חמישיתיו chamishitov in the plural. So that indicates you would not do
a fifth of a fifth if you were then to redeem the
thing that you had then paid, you know, you went ahead and
you sanctified your car. Then you redeemed it by giving I don't
know, you know, by giving a pile of gold to the בית
המקדש and that had a fifth. Then you wanted to redeem that
fifth of gold that you had on something else. Would you add
a fifth to that fifth? So there the פסוק pasuk doesn't clearly
indicate that. ותנן utnan and the משנה mishna says הפודה הקדש מוסיף
חומש. hapodeh hekdesh mosif chomesh.
When you redeem your הקדש, you add a fifth. חומשו תנן וחומשא
דחומשא לא תנן. chomsho tnan vechumsha dechumsha lo tnan.
It says the fifth, it doesn't say a fifth of a fifth.
Okay, so here at least a- you know, so what's the question?
I mean if the משנה mishna doesn't say it and the פסוקים
don't hint to it, shouldn't we conclude that there's no הלכה of
a fifth of a fifth? Let's take a look. מאי, what should
we say? גבי תרומה כתיב ויסף וגבי קדוש נמי כתיב ויסף. gabei
terumah ktiv veyasaf vegabei kadosh nami ktiv veyasaf.
Why by תרומה truma, did we think- what was the hint in
the פסוק pasuk by תרומה that you add a fifth to a
fifth? So I've been saying it's the
חמישיתיו—excuse chamishitav me, no, חמישיתיו chamishitav was by the גזל. gezel. תרומה
did not say חמישיתיו chamishitav in the plural, but it said ויסף.
veyasaf.
So the ויסף, veyasaf, and you should add, so that means that,
you know, and- that means that it's- hold on, try that again.
So by תרומה, even though it didn't say חמישיתיו chamishitav in the
plural, the-
I didn't say this before, the hook in the פסוק pasuk that
we could be sinking would be the- Basis for saying a fifth
of a fifth is that it says ויסף vayasaf and he should
add. So ויסף חמישתו, vayasaf chamishato, so that ויסף vayasaf means adding
on the fifth or a fifth of a fifth. So that's the
question: why do we say by תרומה in the end, what's the
basis in the פסוק pasuk for תרומה by saying a fifth of
a fifth? And do we there- and does that- do we have
a similar type of a basis by הקדש? So let's take a
look at it again.
Okay. מה גבי תרומה כתיב ויסף, גבי קודש נמי כתיב ויסף. Ma
gabei Terumah ketiv vayasaf, gabei kodesh nami ketiv vayasaf. So it both
says ויסף vayasaf add, so that ו-ויסף ve-vayasaf and add means even
more than that, even a fifth of a fifth. או דלמא, O
dilma, is that why we say it by תרומה and then we
would say it by הקדש? Or do we say גבי תרומה כתיב
ויסף? gabei Terumah ketiv vayasaf? Because it says ויסף, vayasaf, it's not
the word יסף yasaf itself or the ו vav of the ויסף
vayasaf and add. It's what we do with the ו. vav. שקלת
ליה לוו דויסף ושדית ליה אחמישתו הוי ליה חמישתיו. Shaklat lei le-vav
de-vayasaf ve-shadyat lei a-chamishato havei lei chamishitav. So
the פסוק pasuk by תרומה is- it says- by the פסוק pasuk
it says כי ויסף חמישתו עליו. ki vayasaf chamishato alav.
So the ו vav of ויסף- vayasaf the ו- vav and we
put it- ויסף חמישתו- vayasaf chamishato the word starts with חמישתו. chamishato.
It's got one ו. vav. If we take the ו vav of
ויסף vayasaf and we put it at the end of the word
חמישתו, chamishato, we have two ו'ס, vavs, חמישתיו, chamishitav, which now means
multiple fifths. Okay, we can play with this by תרומה. By the
פסוק pasuk it says ויסף חמישתו. vayasaf chamishato. If the word ויסף
vayasaf by itself tells us a fifth of a fifth, it would
be true by הקדש. But maybe by תרומה the idea of a
fifth of a fifth is we take the extra ו vav of
ויסף, vayasaf, put it on the end of the word חמישתו, chamishato,
and חמישתו chamishato becomes חמישתיו chamishitav in the plural. That we can
do by תרומה. Okay. גבי הקדש כתיב ויסף חמישית. Gabei Hekdesh ketiv
vayasaf chamishit.
But by הקדש it says you should add a חמישית, chamishit, not
חמישתו. chamishato. אע"ג דשקלת ליה לוו דויסף ושדית ליה אחמישית סוף סוף
הוי ליה חמישתו. Af al gav de-shaklat lei le-vav de-vayasaf ve-shadyat lei
a-chamishit, sof sof havei lei chamishato. It would only be its fifth
in singular. Okay, so that's the question: what's the basis of the
דרשה? derasha? The word ויסף, vayasaf, so we would say it by
הקדש? Or the word חמישתו chamishato plus ויסף, vayasaf, and we wouldn't
say it by הקדש? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: before
answering it, it says, wait a minute, let's try to answer this
question from another direction.
The גמרא Gemara says סוף סוף הוי ליה חמישתו. sof sof havei
lei chamishato. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק ליה דהוי ליה הקדש
שני ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי הקדש ראשון מוסיף חומש הקדש שני
אינו מוסיף חומש. ve-tipok lei de-havei lei Hekdesh sheni ve-amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi Hekdesh rishon mosif chomesh Hekdesh sheni eino mosif chomesh.
So
the גמרא says, wait a minute, before we worry about the fact
that it's a fifth and do you do it on the fifth
of a fifth, there's another reason why you wouldn't add a fifth.
Because according to רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, you
don't add a fifth on anything that's not the original item that
was sanctified. If I go ahead and I sanctify my dresser and
then I transfer it on money and then I want to transfer
it from that money to my car, okay, I wouldn't add a
fifth because the money was- had the stuff that the הקדש was
transferred to, it wasn't the direct object that I sanctified. So wouldn't
that be- meaning forget the idea: is it a fifth or not
a fifth? You wouldn't do a fifth on it because you wouldn't
do a fifth even on the principal that was sanctified because that
was transferred to. I transferred my- I sanctified my dresser, it was
worth eighty. I then transferred it to a pile of gold coins
worth a hundred. Okay, if I now try to transfer that pile
of gold coins, that קדושה kedushah to another thing, I wouldn't add
a fifth because it wasn't the original object that was sanctified. So
why are you bothered about the twenty extra coins of that pile
of a hundred, the eighty versus the twenty? On none of it
should I be adding a fifth because it wasn't the original object
that was sanctified. That's a pretty good question. Let's see what the
גמרא says. אמר ליה רב פפי לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Pappi le-Ravina.
So רב פפי Rav Pappi said to רבינא: הכי אמר רבא. hachi
amar Rava. No, no, no, no, no. חומש כתחלת הקדש דמי. chomesh
ke-tchilat Hekdesh dami. No, no, no, no, no,
that pile of a hundred gold coins, there's a difference between the
eighty and the twenty. The eighty is transferred קדושה. kedushah. The twenty
is new קדושה. kedushah. It fits back to our idea before that
the חומש is an additional thing. It's not you transfer the dresser
onto a hundred coins. You transfer the dresser, which is worth eighty,
onto eighty coins, plus you add an additional twenty coins. So the
eighty is transferred קדושה, kedushah, you don't add a fifth, but the
twenty is new קדושה, kedushah, so you might add a fifth. But
the only question is but it came into the world because... of
the idea of a fifth of the הקדש. So from the idea
of original קדושה kedusha you would add a fifth, but maybe you
don't because ultimately it's a fifth of a fifth, so what's the
הלכה? Very fascinating. Okay, מה הוי לה mah havaylah what's the story?
אמר רב טיבומי משמיה דאביי, Amar Rav Tivumi mishmei de'Abaye, אמר קרא
amar kra the פסוק pasuk says ויסף חמישית כסף ערכך. v'yasaf chamishis
kessef erchecha. You should add the חמישית chamishis of the כסף kessef
of the value. מקיש חומשו לכסף ערכך. Makish chomsho lekessef erchecho.
So the fifth of the כסף kessef of the value normally it
says חמישיתו עליו. But here it says the words of the fifth
and the principal right alongside each other. חמישית כסף ערכך. Chamishis kessef
erchecha. מה כסף ערכו מוסיף חומש Mah kessef ercho mosif chomesh the
same way on the original value you add a fifth, אף כסף
חומשו נמי מוסיף חומש. af kessef chomsho nami mosif chomesh.
Even on the fifth you go ahead and you add a fifth.
Okay, so that's it, it applies by הקדש, it applies by תרומה,
it applies by גזל, gezel, it just doesn't apply by מעשר. גופא
Gufa
let's do one last piece. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi על הקדש ראשון מוסיף חומש על הקדש שני אין
מוסיף חומש. al hekdesh rishon mosif chomesh al hekdesh sheni ein mosif
chomesh. Only on the original thing, not on the transferred קדושה. kedusha.
אמר רבא Amar Rava מאי טעמא mai taima דרבי יהושע בן לוי,
de'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, what's the reason? אמר קרא the פסוק pasuk
says ואם המקדיש יגאל את ביתו. v'im amakdish yig'al es beiso. If
they sanctify redeems his house he adds a fifth. המקדיש ולא המתפיס
Hamakdish v'lo hamatfis
the one who sanctifies not the one who substitutes. Okay, when I
transfer the כסף kessef the money of the the value of the
dresser that was sanctified to the money, it's called I'm מתפיס matfis
the money, I'm not originally sanctifying the money, I'm transferring from the
dresser to the money. And that does not get added a fifth.
Only something I directly sanctified. תני תנא קמיה דרבי אלעזר Tani tana
kemei de'Rabbi Elazar the תנא tana taught in front of רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. ואם בבהמה טמאה ופדה בערכך V'im bivhema teme'ah u'fada b'erchecha
and if it's a you know you sanctified a non-kosher animal you
redeem by the value. מה בהמה טמאה מיוחדת שתחילתו הקדש וכולו לשמים
Ma behema teme'ah meyuchadeshet she'techilaso hekdesh v'kulo lashamayim
so this is a ברייתא that's not going to originally make sense.
The same what's the story about a non-kosher animal? First of all
it's original its sanctity comes
originally, it's not like it comes by something being transferred onto it.
The גמרא is going to say why not? Why can't you have
sanctified something and then transferred it onto a non-kosher animal? But let's
let's go with this for now. The same way a non-kosher animal
was here it was it had original sanctity
because
you sanctified it, and it's all to heaven meaning what? Meaning you
if you sanctify a donkey for example you're going to give it
to the בית המקדש and they're going to use it to carry
loads or they'll redeem it and they'll use the cash. But all
the value goes to the בית המקדש as opposed to if you
sanctify a sheep for let's say a שלמים shlamim then you might
eat some then you'll eat some of the meat so the בית
המקדש doesn't get all of it. Okay, ומועלין בה u'mo'alim bah
and therefore something that was originally קדוש kadosh and all goes to
the בית המקדש מעילה me'ila applies to it. אף כל שתחילתו הקדש
Af kol she'techilaso hekdesh so this would be true by anything, anything
else that originally was קדוש kadosh meaning not originally was born קדוש,
kadosh, it's the original קדושה kedusha not transferred
קדושה kedusha וכולו לשמים מועלין בה v'kulo lashamayim mo'alim bah there's מעילה.
me'ila. Now that's all very bizarre because those are not the parameters
of מעילה me'ila and also the פסוק pasuk of the בהמה טמאה
behema teme'ah was not talking about מעילה. me'ila. So the גמרא is
going to try to get its head around this. אמר ליה רבי
אלעזר לתנא Amar lei Rabbi Elazar le'tana so רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
said to this תנא tana בשלמא כולו לשמים למיעוטי קדשים קלים bishlama
kulo lashamayim limutei kodshim kalim I get when you say it's all
to heaven like I said you know a non-kosher animal's all goes
to the בדק הבית bedek habayis they get the full value would
be contrasting it to שלמים shlamim קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. כיון דאית
להו לבעלים בגווייהו לית בהו מעילה Kevan d'is lehu l'be'alim begavaihu leis
behu me'ila that since the owners don't have a part in of
it then you know no מעילה me'ila would apply at least in
this הוה אמינא hava amina that we're dealing with right now.
Okay, אלא תחילת הקדש למיעוטי מאי? ela techilas hekdesh limutei mai? What
are you coming to say that it was originally sanctified it was
you know had original sanctity and not transferred sanctity? דאימא לעניין תחילת
הקדש דאית
ביה מעילה סוף הקדש לית ביה מעילה? De'ima le'inyan techilas hekdesh d'is
bei me'ila sof hekdesh leis bei me'ila? Do you mean to say
that if I only something I originally sanctifies has מעילה me'ila the
misuse of the prohibition of the misuse of הקדש funds and the
קרבן korban that you bring etc but something that I transfer קדושה
kedusha to does not have מעילה? me'ila? That's not true. Even when
you transfer קדושה kedusha to something it has מעילה. me'ila. So that
can't make sense the way you're teaching this ברייתא. דאימא לעניין חומש
קאמרת De'ima le'inyan chomesh ka'marta כרבי יהושע בן לוי. k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. Maybe when you say מעילה me'ila you don't really mean מעילה
me'ila you really mean like מעלה ma'aleh like something that you add
on to it you raise up to it and you really are
coming to say that when do you add a fifth? Because that
is the context of the פסוק pasuk about adding a fifth. So
it's saying you add a fifth only when it's all to heaven
and it's the original קדושה kedusha not when it's transferred קדושה kedusha
like the teaching of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
that you don't add a fifth. When you are redeeming transferred קדושה
kedusha, *kedusha*. Okay, so אמר ליה *amar lei* he said אינך אין
הכי קאמינא *inoch in hachi kamina*, that's what I meant. Now, the
question is, okay, wait a minute, let's figure this out. We're still
not done. אמר ליה רב אשי לרבינא *amar lei Rav Ashi le-Ravina*,
Rav Ashi said to Ravina, בשלמא בהמה behemah. טמאה מתחילת הקדש איכא
באמצע הקדש ליכא *bishlama behemah temeah mi-tchilat hekdesh ika be-emtza hekdesh leika*?
I don't get it. A non-kosher animal doesn't only have original קדושה
kedusha. *kedusha*, doesn't have transferred קדושה *kedusha*? I can sanctify my cow
and then or whatever, my dresser, and then transfer the קדושה *kedusha*
to my donkey. What do you mean it only has original קדושה
*kedusha*? אמר ליה *amar lei* no, לפי שאינה בסוף הקדש *lefi she-einah
be-sof hekdesh*. No, what it means is is that it's not going
to be something that in the end is going to be used
directly in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Okay, it's not a קרבן
*korban*, it's not a beam that I'm going to build into the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* building. So a non-kosher animal is something that
eventually, it's you know, it doesn't wind up being used for הקדש
*hekdesh* in the end. So אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא *amar
lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina*, Rav Acha mi-Difti said to Ravina, באמצע
הקדש מי איכא *be-emtza hekdesh mi ika*, ולא יוסיף נמי חומש *ve-lo
yosif nami chomesh*? But so what? If it is in the middle,
if I can transfer my dresser to my donkey, so maybe that
should tell us that there is a חומש *chomesh* by transferred קדושה
*kedusha*. How are you learning out that there's no חומש *chomesh* by
transferred קדושה *kedusha* because the תורה *Torah* is talking about a donkey?
A donkey can have transferred קדושה *kedusha*. מי
איכא ולא יוסיף נמי
חומש *mi ika ve-lo yosif nami chomesh*? אמר ליה *amar lei*, הרי
הוא כסוף הקדש וסוף הקדש אינו מוסיף חומש אף אמצע הקדש אינו
מוסיף חומש *harei hu ke-sof hekdesh ve-sof hekdesh eino mosif chomesh af
emtza hekdesh eino mosif chomesh*. No, but because a donkey doesn't have
קדושה *kedusha* סוף הקדש *sof hekdesh*, doesn't have you know, won't end
up being used directly as הקדש *hekdesh*. So since the donkey case
is not in the סוף הקדש *sof hekdesh* category,
then and the donkey case is the case of adding a fifth,
so since adding a fifth is not in the סוף הקדש *sof
hekdesh* category, it's also not in the middle הקדש *hekdesh* category. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says ha, what? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה רב זוטרא בריה דרב מרי לרבינא *amar
lei Rav Zutra brei de-Rav Mari le-Ravina*, מאי חזית דמדמית ליה לסוף
הקדש דמי ליה לתחילת הקדש *mai chazis de-medamit lei le-sof hekdesh dami
lei le-tchilat hekdesh*? The גמרא *Gemara* says like I don't get it.
Why are you sort of saying that you know that like we
should apply the middle case, we should compare to the case
that's at the end, that doesn't isn't the donkey case and there's
no חומש *chomesh*? Maybe we should apply the middle case to the
beginning, which is the donkey case and there is a חומש *chomesh*.
אמר ליה *amar lei*, מסתברא לסוף הקדש הוה ליה לדמויי שכן נתפסת
מנתפסת *mistanbera le-sof hekdesh hava lei le-damuyei she-ken nitpeset mi-nitpeset*. No, no,
no, because the thing at the end, if we go dresser to
donkey
to a beam in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, that was the
process. So if the beam doesn't have a fifth because it's the
end thing that's going to be used,
then the donkey also shouldn't because they're both similar in that
the I don't know the right but anyway, they're both similar in
that I mean let's see, a donkey to a dresser to a
beam, okay. So if the whatever, a donkey to a donkey to
a beam, whatever. Anyway, if the beam doesn't because it's the end
thing that's going to be used,
then the middle thing also shouldn't because they're both similar in that
they're not the original הקדש *hekdesh*. So maybe that's why the end
doesn't have it, so that's the comparison. אדרבה לתחילת הקדש הוה ליה
לדמויי שכן דבר שיש אחריו קדושה בדבר שיש אחריו קדושה *aderaba le-tchilat
hekdesh hava lei le-damuyei she-ken davar she-yesh acharov kedusha be-davar she-yesh acharov
kedusha*. Okay,
but let's compare it, I don't understand, it's like why do we
still say this middle case doesn't, you don't add a fifth, because
we're comparing it to the last case? The end of the קדושה
*kedusha* is transferred and you don't add a fifth, so the middle
case is transferred and you also don't add a fifth. Let's say
the opposite. The first case you do add a fifth because something
is coming after it. So the middle case you also add a
fifth because there's going to be a קדושה *kedusha* coming after it.
So bottom line is we know the first case you add a
fifth, the original הקדש *hekdesh*. We know the way it ends up
you're not redeeming it, so you're not adding a fifth. How do
we know what the status is about something in the middle and
how are you learning that out from this case of the donkey?
It makes no sense. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
so כדאמר רבא *ked-amar Rava*, because Rava teaches so you're right. It's
not about beginning, middle, end or whatever, it's a different דרשה *drasha*.
העולה *ha-olah*, עולה Olah ראשונה *olah rishonah*, הכי נמי הטמאה טמאה ראשונה
*hachi nami ha-temeah temeah rishonah*. Fine,
says the גמרא *Gemara*. It's not based on beginning, middle, end. It's
based on the ה he *hei*. Like when the פסוק *pasuk* says
by צו *Tzav*, היא העולה על מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה *hi
ha-olah al mokdah al ha-mizbeiach kol ha-layla*, and from which we learn
it's talking about the עולה *olah* mentioned in the beginning of that
פרשה *parsha* is the עולת תמיד *olas tamid* because ה *hei*. עולה
means the first עולה that's being offered up,
so when it says בהמה הטמאה Behemah Ha-tmeiah it means the first
הבהמה הטמאה, Ha-behemah Ha-tmeiah,
it means the first בהמה. So the first one is the one
that gets transferred, that gets a fifth, not one that comes after.
So we're not saying that a non-kosher animal cannot be a middle
קדושה, a transferred קדושה. It can. But the פסוק that says you
add a fifth, that says הבהמה הטמאה, ha-behemah ha-tmeiah, אם בבהמה הטמאה,
im bi-vhemah ha-tmeiah,
that ה is telling you we're only talking about the first thing
sanctified and not something to which it is transferred from. And that
something transferred you do not add a fifth. Okay, we will end
here.